Today's דף daf is קמט, Kuf Mem Tet, 149, and we are
dealing with different parameters of מתנת שכיב מרע matnat Shchiv Mera and
what we just dealt with yesterday was that this main difference which
basically determines are you in this rabbinic category of מתנת שכיב מרע
matnat Shchiv Mera when it's כל נכסיו, kol nechasav, which you could
have a קנין kinyan but it's unnecessary and the key being אמר
חוזר, amar chozer, well there are two keys, a, the קנין kinyan
is necessary, b, אמר חוזר, amar chozer, what is the line between
כל נכסיו kol nechasav and מקצת נכסיו? miktzat nechasav? And that's something
that we're going to continue to revisit, but at one point the
גמרא Gemara says even if it looks like it's כל נכסיו, kol
nechasav, maybe it's not. You know, maybe there's some property that we
don't know about, right, and that would basically put many more situations
into the אמדי לא חוזר, amdi lo chozer, which would be a
discouragement for people to employ this whole type of a device. Now
there are ways around that, right? I mean if we know it's
all your property, if you explicitly maybe say it's all your property,
but anyway that was interesting exactly trying to draw that line. And
then the גמרא Gemara dealt with some more technical question about that
if you gave it all and then you retract, was it a
full retraction or a partial retraction with all of the implications about
which of those was a straight קנין kinyan and which of those
was a מתנת שכיב מרע? matnat Shchiv Mera? Okay, so now the
גמרא Gemara says like this, איבעיא להו, iba'ya lehu, we pick up
seven lines from the bottom on קמח עמוד ב, Kuf Mem Chet
Amud Bet,
eight lines from the bottom, איבעיא להו, iba'ya lehu, they ask the
following question: הקדיש כל נכסיו ועמד מהו, hikdish kol nechasav ve'amad mahu,
somebody didn't give it away, sanctified it to the בית המקדש, Beis
Hamikdash, they're on their deathbed and they say all of my money
should go to the בית המקדש. Beis Hamikdash. Okay, so if he
were to die, fine, that would be a מתנת שכיב מרע matnat
Shchiv Mera to the בית המקדש, Beis Hamikdash, thank you very much,
okay, but if he got up, would he have the same principle
of אמר חוזר? amar chozer? Okay, what would we say? Would we
say because you know normally the guy's giving it because he thinks
he's going to die, if he gets better he doesn't, he doesn't
want to be left penniless. Okay, but on the other hand, it's
to the בית המקדש, Beis Hamikdash, so who knows? You know, for
all we know, maybe he's making this deal with God in his
head, you know, I'm going to give all, I'll give all the
money if I get better, so maybe אדרבה, adaraba, if he gets
better then, you know, then that's why the money should go to
the בית המקדש. Beis Hamikdash. Okay, so what do we think is
going on there? I mean, so הקדיש כל נכסיו ועמד מהו. hikdish
kol nechasav ve'amad mahu. מי אמרינן, mi amrinan, do we say כל
לגבי הקדש גמר ומקני, kol lgabei hekdesh gamar u'makni, if it's for
the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash he just wants the בית המקדש Beis
Hamikdash to own it regardless of whether he gets better? או דלמא,
o dilma, or do we say כל לגבי נפשיה לא גמר ומקני?
kol lgabei nafshei lo gamar u'makni? No, at the end of the
day, he's got himself to take care of. It's all very nice
for the בית המקדש, Beis Hamikdash, but if he gets better, he's
going to need that money. Okay, so therefore he is not, if
we're on the other side of the equation, he wants to make
sure that if he's better, he still has the money.
Okay, so we don't know the answer. So now let's ask the
next question. Now, does the next question assume, you know, normally the
next question is building on the previous one. So it seems like
רשב"ם Rashbam says the opposite of this, but it seems like it's
sort of saying, even if you say that in the case of
the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash he's not giving it, okay, he's not
going to, he wants to get it back if he gets better,
what would you say about the following case? הפקיר כל נכסיו מהו,
hifkir kol nechasav mahu, let's say he was הפקיר mafkir it, okay,
after I die it should be any, you know, anybody can come
and take it. Okay, what do we say? מי אמרינן, mi amrinan,
do we say כיון דאף לעניים כעשירים גמר ומקני, keivan de'af le'aniym
k'ashirim gamar u'makni,
since he's making it available even to the poor, meaning maybe okay,
the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash is still, you know, a, you know,
God and the בית המקדש, Beis Hamikdash, but you know, the בית
המקדש Beis Hamikdash entirely most times was pretty well endowed. Okay, so
here maybe the guy figures look, I'm being הפקיר, mafkir, I'm giving
the poor an option to take it, they really need the money.
Okay, so therefore maybe given that he wants them to have it
even if he gets better. או דלמא, o dilma, or do we
say כל לגבי נפשיה לא גמר ומקני? kol lgabei nafshei lo gamar
u'makni? No, at the end of the day, it's nice that the
poor need money, but I also need money and if I'm going
to get better, I wouldn't, I don't want it to go over
to them, it only, you know, was only under the circumstances of
his death.
Okay, so we don't know. Now let's assume that in that case
he would say if he gets better it follows the normal rule
and he gets it back, and the same by הקדש. hekdesh. How
about the third case? חילק כל נכסיו לעניים מהו? chilek kol nechasav
le'aniym mahu? Let's say he's giving it to the poor, not just
the rich and the poor. I want it all to be given
to צדקה. tzedakah. Okay, what do we say? Do we say מי
אמרינן, mi amrinan, צדקה ודאי מיגמר גמר ומקני, tzedakah vadai migmar gamar
u'makni, if it's for
צדקה, tzedakah, you know, directly to the poor who ממש mamash need
the money and they're ממש mamash starving or whatever, you know, they
don't, so there really he wants them to have it even if
he gets better. או דלמא, o dilma, כל לגבי נפשיה לא גמר
ומקני? kol lgabei nafshei lo gamar u'makni? No, at the end of
the day, he still has himself to take care of. You know,
you could ask, what about for the rest of his life? He
wasn't giving all his money away to the poor. Okay, so anyway,
תיקו, teiku, so we don't know. It's an interesting the way you
read the progression. I read it the way I think the language
of the גמרא Gemara makes it sound, which is that even if
you assume he's keeping it for the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash and
keeping it in the case of הפקר, hefker, maybe he would give
it away to the poor. רשב"ם Rashbam reads it the other way:
even if you assume by הקדש hekdesh he wants הקדש hekdesh to
have it, and even if you assume that by when he's הפקיר
mafkir he wants it to be הפקר, hefker, maybe for the poor
he doesn't, which doesn't sound that way from the גמרא. Gemara. It's
an interesting question to sort of think about, you know, the... Psychology.
Is a person like, you know, I mean I think that's often,
I think sadly, maybe this is not true, but people give to,
you know, to like things that feel more religious rather than to
the, you know, more like the בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash they give
rather than giving to the poor, right? People probably give more money
to the שול, shul, right, than they give to, you know, to
some fund that's taking care of the poor people in the community,
right? You know, or people give more to the Metropolitan Museum of
Art, which is very wealthy, right, than they'll give to, you know,
dealing with poverty in the Bronx or something like that. So I
think it's interesting, you know, whether the psychology is, oh, if it's
the poor then you definitely want them to have it. That's the
way I read it, which is the language of the גמרא, Gemara,
אודאי מיגמר גמור ומקני. avada migmar gamur umakni. But the way the
רשב"ם Rashbam reads it is like, no, you know, maybe by the
בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash you want the בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash to
have it, but maybe by the poor you're going to want to
keep it in the end if you get better. I don't see
how that fits the language, but I do think it's an interesting
psychological question, right? About which—what are people more ready to give their
money to? Yes.
But it seems like with הקדש, hekdesh, it's the only one where
you've got a principle
on the countervailing side against the שכיב מרע shechiv mera if he
recovers gets it back. Because any other kind of gift,
it's not if you're going to give a gift to poor people
that you can't ever get it back, whereas with הקדש hekdesh there's
that principle— What do you mean?
If I—oh, if somebody gives a gift to the poor, he can't
get it back once he's given it.
I'm not
understanding— if it's a—if it's a pledge let's say.
Okay, so that's true, but the difference of a שכיב מרע shechiv
mera meaning it's true that
if somebody makes a pledge then they're bound to it because of
the laws of נדרים. nedarim. But if somebody actually give it—gave it
to them, I gave it to the גבאי צדקה gabbai tzedakah and
he took the money, like I drove my car to Cars for
Kids and I deposited it in the Cars for Kids lot, right,
then that's it, I can't get it back after that. And the
words of a שכיב מרע shechiv mera are more—are like that act
of קנין, kinyan, not just like that act of נדר, neder, right?
The words of the שכיב מרע shechiv mera are like you handed
it over. So in all of these under normal circumstances if you
actually did a קנין kinyan it would be too late. You are
right that הקדש hekdesh is similar, that הקדש hekdesh is the one
case where the קנין kinyan is effected by the words,
right? Even by—well, no, הפקר hefker also, the transition of status is
effected by the words. And נדר neder it's not yet there, but
it's—I mean צדקה tzedakah it's not yet there, but it's a נדר.
neder. But I don't see the difference along those lines once the
act of a שכיב מרע—but shechiv mera I think—so, alright,
but let's go on. So the גמרא Gemara says so it doesn't
know. לשון אחר, Lashon acher, הקדיש כל נכסיו מהו, hikdish kol nechasav
mahu, הפקיר כל נכסיו מהו, hifkir kol nechasav mahu, חילק כל נכסיו
לעניים מהו, chilek kol nechasav la'aniyim mahu, תיקו. teiku. That's a short
version of it, but it's a little less interesting because it doesn't
spell out what the thoughts are on either side and it doesn't
give you a sense of the progression. Okay, so anyway, so that's
interesting, right? Does this apply in those types of cases? But what
we're also introduced with in addition to the question of אם עמד
חוזר im amad chozer is that the הלכה halacha that דברי שכיב
מרע divrei shechiv mera are binding works, you know, not just by
a normal person receiving a gift, right? I mean, you know, Goya
was right to point out הקדש hekdesh and הפקר hefker can work
purely by a verbal act even without a שכיב מרע. shechiv mera.
But giving it to the עניים, aniyim, right, that's it's a little
bit in a grayer zone. But anyway, but it sounds like the
impact of דברי שכיב מרע divrei shechiv mera works there as well
to make it a full קנין. kinyan. Okay now the גמרא Gemara
says like this: אמר רב ששת, amar Rav Sheshet,
יטול ויזכה ויחזיק ויקנה, yitol ve'yizke ve'yachzik ve'yikne, let's say somebody in
his צוואה, tzava'ah, in his like you know will, or his verbal
will or his written
will says 'somebody should be קונה koneh all my נכסים,' nechasim, or
'should take my נכסים,' nechasim, יטול yitol Reuven, יזכה yizke
Reuven, יחזיק yachzik he's take possession of,
יקנה, yikne, כולם לשון מתנה הן, kulam lashon matanah hen, all of
those are the right technical terms for gifting the property in a
מתנת שכיב מרע matnat shechiv mera and they work. Okay, במתניתא
תנא, bematnita tana, and obviously we're going to contrast it in a
minute to some terms that don't work. In the ברייתא Baraita we
taught, אף יחסן ויירש, af yachsin ve'yeiraish, okay, even if you say
let him inherit, those are two versions of the words inherit. Okay,
so now really? Inherit are words of a שכיב מרע? shechiv mera?
This gets to this question of is the שכיב מרע shechiv mera
a gift or a pseudo-inheritance?
So there's two points, one is how do you frame it, and
the other is like what effect does it take? So we dealt
with ways in which its effect is effective like an inheritance, by
gifting a loan for example. But are you allowed to explicitly describe
it as a ירושה? yerushah? Or maybe you, the guy on the
deathbed, have to describe it as a מתנה, matanah, but then halachically
the way it's treated is as a type of ירושה? yerushah? I
know it's a funny hybrid, but at the end of the day,
you know, your more obvious powers are those by giving a מתנה.
matanah. So the ברייתא Baraita has a language
of ירושה. yerushah. But the גמרא Gemara qualifies it and says בראוי
ליורשו רבי יוחנן בן ברוקא היא. bera'uy leyorsho Rabbi Yochanan ben Beroka
hi. That's really not a standard language of a שכיב מרע. shechiv
mera. If a שכיב מרע shechiv mera says that Reuven inherits this
property, it would only work if Reuven is some degree of an
heir, and
it
was— or can he even be a second and a third level
heir and you can bring him up to being a first level,
right those were questions within רבי יוחנן בן ברוקא, Rabbi Yochanan ben
Broka, but the גמרא Gemara here saying fine, that language works within
the world of רבי יוחנן בן ברוקא, Rabbi Yochanan ben Broka, but
not within the standard world of שכיב מרע. Sheciv Meira. Okay, or
not for a שכיב מרע Sheciv Meira if we don't פוסקן pasken
like רבי יוחנן בן ברוקא. Rabbi Yochanan ben Broka. Then again, that's
interesting, that's saying that putting aside רבי יוחנן בן ברוקא, Rabbi Yochanan
ben Broka, שכיב מרע Sheciv Meira has to use language of מתנה,
matana, not language of ירושה. yerusha. But that does not end the
discussion of whether we conceptualize it, the impact of it, you know,
as at the end of the day a ירושה yerusha or מתנה,
matana, we've already seen before aspects of ירושה yerusha we're going to
continue to see that. But the language bracketing רבי יוחנן בן ברוקא
Rabbi Yochanan ben Broka has to be language of מתנה. matana. Yes.
I was just going to say, and not for me to go
back to that סוגיא sugia that right about אמדינן דעתא, Amdinan Daata,
אמדינן
דעתי.
Amdinan
Daate.
אמדינן דעתי. Amdinan Daate.
No, I'm well I'm not sure which one you're talking about. The
אמדינן דעתי Amdinan Daate partly was אם עמד חוזר, im amad chozer,
but the real direct issue about whether we about aspects of looking
at it like a ירושה yerusha was for example different explanations of
why a שכיב מרע Sheciv Meira can give a loan. Can he
give over a loan because it's because a יורש yoresh would receive
a loan. But there were other explanations, maybe because of מעמד שלשתן,
Ma'amad Shelishtan, and yes.
This distinction whether it's an inheritance or a gift. This would have
consequences if some of these applies in secular law
because inheritances are taxed very differently from gifts in probably most countries.
Right, well the other case is well we don't have the taxes
here, but also I want to remind you of the whole discussion
of if he gave it away by מתנת שכיב מרע, matnat Sheciv
Meira, does the אלמנה almana and the daughters still have their rights
to the property because wouldn't have it if he had gifted it
or sold it he wouldn't they would have it against the heir.
Right? So there's big differences. Yep. So let's take a look.
In US law you don't have a difference between gift and inheritance.
Really? You get an annual certain amount that you can gift free
of tax. Thereafter
gifts during your lifetime get accumulated and applied against the credit for
your estate tax.
Oh really? That's a... Alright alright. We're moving on. We're moving on.
יהנא בהן מאי? Yehana bahen mai? Okay? So מהי? mahi? Let's say
the person on his deathbed said, 'Let פלוני Ploni derive benefit from
my house.' Okay, what does that mean?
מהי? mahi? דליהוי כולה מתנה d'leihavei kullah matana אמר amar is he
saying let him derive benefit because let it all be his. You
know what, every time, you know, John would see me in my
Ferrari he would so appreciate, I said I wasn't mentioning the Ferrari
yet, he would so appreciate it, you know what, he should get
the benefit of the Ferrari. Okay, so am I saying that he
should own it? And therefore by owning it he should derive the
benefit or am I saying like, you know, my kids should let
him drive it around once a week. Okay? או דילמא לאיתהנויי מניהו
דקאמר, o dilma l'ithenuyei mineihu d'ka amar, let him get some benefit
from it. Okay?
יראה בהן מהו, yeiraeh bahen mahu, let him be seen with them.
Okay, does that mean seen with them as the as the owner?
Okay, or does it mean, you know, let him sometimes have an
opportunity to, you know, be seen with the car. Or יעמוד בהן
מהו, yaamod bahen mahu, let him stand in them. Does that mean
rely upon them like you stand on your property, you know, you
rely on it, it's yours? Or does it mean, you know, just
some way of get some benefit. ישען בהן, yishaein bahen, lean on
them. Again, that's even more clear, you know, get support from them.
Because again, because it ממש mammash should be his or somehow you
should, you know, you've got this large estate let ראובן Reuven get
some support from it. Okay, if you said the word some it
would be more obvious, right? But let him be let him be
supported by it. Supported by it would mean give him some annuity
or does it mean let him own it? תיקו. teiku. So we
don't know about all of those. So I assume the הלכה halacha
would be like המוציא מחברו עליו הראיה, hamotzi meichaveiro alav haraaya, that
the יורשים yorshim would be considered the מוחזק muchzak and the other
person would somehow have the burden of proof, but it would be
interesting how that would get adjudicated. What if he would seize it,
you know, or something. Okay, איבעיא להו, ibayalu, they asked the following
question.
לא קנה. lo kana.
רמב"ם Rambam says לא קנה. lo kana. Okay, doesn't even say like
it's a מחלוקת machloket or whatever. Interesting.
What does the שולחן ערוך Shulchan Aruch say? חושן משפט Choshen Mishpat
רנ"ג ב'. resh nun gimmel bet.
Hold on. Now now you're making me look up the הלכה. halacha.
Okay, let's take a look.
It's not
even here.
Michael,
exactly. רנ"ג ב'. resh nun gimmel bet.
לא קנה. lo kana.
לא קנה. lo kana. Just a straight לא קנה. lo kana. Interesting.
So it's interesting that the resolution of a תיקו teiku is לא
קנה. lo kana. I mean you could understand it, right? It's ודאי
vadai the יורשים, yorshim, it's a ספק safek whether this רבנן rabbanan
institution should be applied, so we ודאי vadai wouldn't apply it. But
that's interesting. That they're פוסק paskening ודאי vadai not ספק. safek. Okay.
איבעיא להו. Ibaia lehu. So they ask the following question. מכר כל
נכסיו מהו? Machar kol nechasav mahu? Now this is a case of
somebody's on his deathbed, you can totally imagine this. Somebody's on his
deathbed, he's got all of these holdings, and before he's dying, he's
trying to figure out how to liquidate his assets. Okay? And he
liquidates his entire assets, and then he gets better. So do we
say עמד חוזר? amad chozer? Why was the reason עמד חוזר? amad
chozer? This is important. The reason עמד חוזר amad chozer is not
just because you're employing this rabbinic, this new rabbinic institution called מתנת
שכיב מרע. matnas shchiv mera. It would be true even if you
did a קניין. kinyan. A קניין kinyan wasn't necessary, but even if
you were working without the rabbinic institution of מתנת שכיב מרע, matnas
shchiv mera, עמד חוזר. amad chozer. What is the reason the גמרא
Gemara says? אמדינן דעתיה, amdinan dateih, right? We do an אומדנא דעתא.
umdna de'ata. Okay, right? Because we assume the guy's only doing it
because he's expecting to die. He wouldn't do it if he didn't
want to die. So if that's true, let's say the guy just
sold it. He liquidated his assets, and then he got better. Well,
presumably he was only doing it because he was expecting to die,
so maybe the whole thing would be reversed. Now you might remember,
by the way, now first of all, so the pushback about that
is two. Number one pushback is is that, you know, maybe, you
know, maybe he's selling it for other reasons even if he's not
going to die, you know, he wants his assets liquidated or whatever.
It's not as obvious, okay? But number two is the more interesting
point from my end is remember I said that the whole idea
that we go by what you're thinking and not by, we are
able to go by what you're thinking and not only by what
you said, why don't we say דברים שבלב אינם דברים, devarim shebalev
einam devarim, is because when we're dealing with one-sided transactions,
a מתנה matana or a גט. get. A מכר mecher is a
two-sided transaction. So what should immediately kick in is the rule of
דברים שבלב אינם דברים. devarim shebalev einam devarim. This guy is selling
it on his deathbed. He's liquidating all of his stocks and his
assets. So everybody else, he's not stipulating in the case that I
die, all of a sudden now you're going to reverse the sale?
Is that really fair to all those other people? Right? So that's
your classic דברים שבלב אינם דברים. devarim shebalev einam devarim. So it
doesn't matter what he's thinking. He didn't say it and there's somebody
else who's actually part of that transaction.
But if he still has all his assets, it's just in another
form.
Well, that's the question. Okay, yes, right. Meaning it wouldn't be so
bad. It's exactly. Meaning that's the other reason to say it shouldn't
be reversed. At the end of the day, it's not like he,
he still has the money to bequeath to his heirs. He still
has the money to pay for his own support until he dies.
It's just now in cash form. So there's a million reasons why
we should not say
עמד חוזר, amad chozer, right?
It wasn't a gift, was it?
Exactly. He didn't give it away. He just sold it. He just
changed it from one form to another. Now the reality is that
it might not be as good for him to have just plain
cash as it was to have all of these properties and income
investments or whatever. Okay, but you know what, at the end of
the day, it's not like, you know, it's not like he lost
it all.
So he can buy other property, he can go back.
Exactly, exactly, exactly.
Right, but the reason why you can ask this question is that
the לוקח lokeach in the מכירה mechira needs to know he's taking
a risk. He's buying from a שכיב מרע, shchiv mera, from a
deathbed,
and there's
a 30-day period where you've got to wait until...
So he's only taking a risk if this law is true. But
the other way to say that is if the guy knows it's
a שכיב מרע, shchiv mera, maybe it's not just דברים שבלב. devarim
shebalev. Meaning it's a type of דברים שבלב כל אדם. devarim shebalev
kol adam. It's self-evident to everybody, you know, it should be self-evident
even to the buyers that the guy was selling it because he
was expecting to die. So a, you know, so that might not
always be true. It might not always be so self-evident, you know?
And again, that's why we have generally have the rule of דברים
שבלב אינם דברים. devarim shebalev einam devarim. But okay, you could imagine
that we might assume maybe that's part of the reason why we
should say it is חוזר. chozer. Maybe it is pretty evident that
that's why it's being done. So let's see what the גמרא Gemara
says. What?
Is אנן סהדי? anan sahadi?
Yeah, so אנן סהדי anan sahadi is a way of saying דברים
שבלב כל אדם, devarim shebalev kol adam, you know? It's no longer
דברים שבלב. devarim shebalev. It's like it's already said if it's obvious.
Okay. But it also assumes that everybody's doing business with people face-to-face,
you know, and I see your circumstances or whatever as opposed to
through our lawyers, right? Who knows? Okay. So the גמרא Gemara says
like this. So it's a really interesting question. So איבעיא להו: Ibaia
lehu: מכר כל נכסיו מהו? Machar kol nechasav mahu? אמר רב יהודה
אמר רב, Amar Rav Yehuda amar Rav, אם עמד אינו חוזר. im
amad eino chozer. It's okay,
it doesn't go back. Sorry. For all the reasons we said, you
still have money, it's a two-sided transaction. וזימנין אמר רב יהודה אמר
רב, ve-zimnin amar Rav Yehuda amar Rav, but some say it was
said in the name of רב, Rav, אם עמד חוזר. im amad
chozer. It does go back. Okay. So it could just be that
he kept on changing his mind, but the גמרא Gemara tries to,
tries to say that it depends on the circumstances. לא פליגי. Lo
pligi. הא דאית ליה זוזי בעינייהו והא דפרעינהו
בחובו. Ha de-is leh zuzei be-einaihu ve-ha de-parinehu be-chovo. Are you liquidating
your assets and then paying off all the debts? In that type
of a case, עמד אינו חוזר, amad eino chozer, okay, because whereas
if you're liquidating the assets and you have the money sitting around,
okay, and still in your bank account, we would say עמד חוזר.
amad chozer. Why? What do you think the difference is between if
the money was used to pay off the debts or not?
Any thoughts?
If the money is used to pay off the debts, you can't
undo the transaction.
Right. So if the money is used to pay off the debts,
then once you... Going ahead and applying it for that purpose, clearly
he's not intending that that to hold up the opportunity to reverse
it, whereas if he hasn't done anything with the money and he
wants to keep that option available, so clearly from the very beginning
his intent was was that if he's that if he's, you know,
survives, that he's going to want to reverse it. Of course, to
some degree then it shouldn't just be a question of what he
did with the money afterwards, it should be what his intent was
when he was selling it, right? Let's say we knew he was
selling it in order to pay off his debts and he hadn't
gotten around to paying off his debts yet, but okay, and before
he got better, okay, he was making arrangements to pay off his
debts and whatever and oh, he got better, right? So, you know,
presumably that should be like עמד אינו חוזר, amad eino chozer, it's
clear he was trying to pay off his debts. So anyway, it's
not clear. But the other, but the question is still what's also,
what's in my mind is interesting is that we do allow for
some cases in here of עמד חוזר amad chozer even though it
was a two-sided transaction. And even though I would be more inclined,
I would be more inclined to say דברים שבלב אינם דברים. devarim
shebalev einam devarim. But again, maybe it's because most cases of a
שכיב מרע shachiv mera are not just דברים שבלב, devarim shebalev, they're
clear to everybody who's involved that that's the context. Okay, so now
the גמרא Gemara says like this: איבעיא להו. ibaya lehu.
שכיב מרע שהודה מהו? shachiv mera shehoda mahu? Let's say a שכיב
מרע shachiv mera does not say, "I want Ploni to have this
field." Let's say he says, "You know what? This field always was
Reuven's. I know everybody thought it was mine, but really all my
life I stole it, or Reuven let me use it," or whatever
the case might be. "This car, my beautiful Ferrari, it really was,
it always was Reuven's." Now he might be totally lying, you know,
but it doesn't matter because interestingly in הלכה, halacha, one way to
create
property realities
is to sort of make false claims against yourself. I know it
sounds very strange,
but if I basically come in front of witnesses and I testify
that this beautiful סטענדער shtender here, you know, belongs to Gloria, okay,
then, then it belongs to Gloria, because that my self-admission is evidence
against me, okay, and whether or not it was or was not
true as an objective fact, now as a matter of law, since
I admitted to it in front of witnesses in a way that
I couldn't just say afterwards I was just kidding around, you know,
I did it in a, in a serious context, then the בית
דין beit din will פסקין pasken it belongs to Gloria.
Even if she doesn't have to make a קנין. kinyan.
Right, she doesn't have to make a קנין kinyan and even if,
even if all the evidence is against it, right? You know, even
if you saw me take money that I earned at my job
and walk to the store with that money and buy the סטענדער
shtender and I said I'm buying it for myself, and there was
never a question, and two minutes later there's never any question, we
had absolute
incontrovertible facts that contradict that claim, when I say I'm מודה modeh
that this belongs to Gloria, now it goes against all other evidence
and it belongs to her.
Unbelievable. If I take your סטענדער shtender and go to court and
say it belongs to Gloria...
No, that doesn't mean anything. Okay, so that's the problem, that's the
idea of הודאת בעל דין כמאה עדים דמי. hodaat baal din kemeah
edim dami. So then, actually so this is by the way a
great way as we're going to see to work around that messy
need of having to do קנינים, kinyanim, because you could just admit
to something that's counterfactual, but if you're saying it against yourself and
you're saying and you still need to satisfy certain conditions, has to
be witnesses, has to be sort of clear that you're being serious
and not kidding around, but then it has the effect of making
it belong to that other person. So the question is, so what
if a שכיב מרע shachiv mera did this? Now the question is,
well why should that not be good if a normal person can
do this? And a שכיב מרע shachiv mera has more power than
a normal person, and he can verbally transfer, so certainly he should
be able to just verbally say that something belongs to somebody, like
something of his is already owned by somebody, that's what a normal
person can do. So the רשב"ם Rashbam says, well the reason that
we're asking it is not because of the extra power of a
שכיב מרע, shachiv mera, it's actually because here there's a reason to
say it shouldn't work by שכיב מרע, shachiv mera, because there's a
גמרא Gemara elsewhere that says that if somebody on his deathbed says,
"You know, I owe a million dollars to Reuven" or whatever, that
actually we would not believe the person. Why would we not believe
them? Because they would say, because we say maybe he's doing it
so people don't think that his kids have all of this money
now, and now everybody's going to be, you know, trying to get
money off of, you know, he's leaving behind these young kids who
are not, you know, savvy, and people are going to be trying
to like, you know, take advantage of them or whatever, so he'd
rather people think that he's not so well off, okay? So that's
the phrase called שלא להשביע את בניו, shelo lehasbia et banav, you
know, not to make his kids look wealthy. So sometimes we are
discounting claims that a שכיב מרע shachiv mera makes about money that
belongs that he owes or that belongs other people. So what would
be the case here? Okay, so the, now so let's take a
look at what the גמרא Gemara says, okay? So would a שכיב
מרע shachiv mera be work just like according to again the רשב"ם
Rashbam not his special power, but just like if a normal person
admits that something of his belongs to somebody else, we believe him,
what about a שכיב מרע? shachiv mera? שכיב מרע שהודה מהו, shachiv
mera shehoda mahu, what would be the story? תא שמע, ta shema,
come and hear. דאיסר גיורא, de'Issur Giyora, there was this... Let's take
a look at what the גמרא Gemara says, okay? So would a
שכיב מרע shchiv meira work just like according to the גמרא's Gemara
מתנת matnas special power, but just if a normal person admits that
something of his belongs to somebody else we believe him, what about
a שכיב מרע? shchiv meira? שכיב מרע שהודה מהו, shchiv meira she-hoda
mahu, what would be the story? תא שמע, Ta shma, come in
here. דאיסור גיורא, De-Issur Giyora, there was this non-Jew who had converted
and his name was איסור Issur the גר, Ger, okay? Actually, it's
an interesting story. He actually had taken captive one of the daughters
of שמואל, Shmuel, who was named רחל, Rachel, and and had intercourse
with her, and she conceived, and then he converted while she was
pregnant, okay? And the child, and the child we'll see was רב
מרי בר רחל, Rav Mari bar Rachel, okay? Because רחל Rachel was,
he was named after his mother because his mother was שמואל's Shmuel
daughter and not his father who had been a non-Jew at the
time. But then he had converted and now he was living in
the Jewish community. הוו ליה תריסר אלפי זוזי בי רבא. havu lei
treisar alfei zuzei bei Rava. He had twelve thousand זוזי zuzei
over in רבא's Rava house, meaning either that רבא Rava had borrowed
it from him or that רבא Rava was watching it for him,
okay? It seems more like it was the money was like just
in the, like it actually was like the cash was there, okay?
He had that being
given to רבא Rava for safe keeping.
So, בי רבא. bei Rava. מרי בריה, Mari breih, now מרי Mari
his son was רב מרי בר רחל. Rav Mari bar Rachel. הורתו
שלא בקדושה, horaso she-lo b'kedusha, he was conceived not in sanctity, meaning
he was conceived when his father had been a non-Jew. It's funny
because רב מרי Rav Mari was always a Jew because his mother
was Jewish, but he was conceived when his father wasn't Jewish. ולידתו
בקדושה, v'lidaso b'kedusha, and he was born in sanctity. But again, that's
normally used when the woman converts when she's pregnant, because therefore the
fetus was conceived not in sanctity, the mother wasn't Jewish, and then
born in sanctity after the mother had been Jewish. Here, the mother
all along had been Jewish, okay? But he was conceived when his
father wasn't Jewish and born when his father was Jewish. So halachically,
is he related to his father?
What do you think?
So he was conceived his father was a non-Jew. So now his
father is Jewish, so his father is considered halachically a different person
than the man who conceives him, okay? So he's not related to
his father, okay?
That's
why they call him בר רחל, bar Rachel, exactly. Okay, so yeah,
הוי. havai. ובי רב הוה, u'vei Rav hava, and he was a
student in ישיבה. yeshiva. All right. אמר רבא, Amar Rava, said רבא,
Rava, היכי קנינהו רב מרי להני זוזי? heichi kaninhu Rav Mari l'hanei
zuzei? So רבא, Rava, remember, who is the one who has all
this cash in his, you know, in his safety deposit box, is
holding onto this cash, said, clearly this איסור גיורא Issur Giyora wanted
this money to go to his son, not his legal son, but
whatever, but his biological son, okay? So רבא Rava was saying, and
רבא's Rava the one holding onto this cash, how would רב מרי
Rav Mari be able to take possession of this money? אי בירושה,
ee b'yerusha, if we're just going to say that his father's going
to die so he'll inherit it, לאו בר ירושה הוא. lav bar
yerusha hu. So he he can't inherit. He's not halachically related to
his father. אי במתנה, ee b'matana, let's say the father will give
it to him as a מתנת שכיב מרע. matnas shchiv meira. So
מתנת שכיב מרע כירושה שויוה רבנן. matnas shchiv meira k'yerusha shavyuha rabanan.
I told you we were going to see this again. It's not
a straight מתנה. matana. It has to work like a ירושה. yerusha.
Now, כל היכא דליתא בירושה ליתא במתנה. kol heicha d'leisa b'yerusha leisa
b'matana. If the person can't get, if ירושה yerusha isn't relevant, a
מתנה matana isn't relevant. Now, who is ליתא בירושה leisa b'yerusha in
this equation? Who is the person for whom ירושה yerusha is not
relevant and they are, is it do you think it's רב מרי
Rav Mari or do you think it's איסור גיורא? Issur Giyora? You
think it's איסור גיורא? Issur Giyora? You think it's הגיורא ha-Giyora because
איסור גיורא Issur Giyora does not right now have any heirs, right?
So I thought so also initially, and that would mean that if
anybody is a גר, ger, they can't use מתנת שכיב מרע. matnas
shchiv meira. But it's first of all it's not true, because a
גר ger could have kids after they're converting,
so they are איתא בירושה. isa b'yerusha. So the person who is
ליתא בירושה leisa b'yerusha is רב מרי, Rav Mari, because רב מרי
Rav Mari has nobody that that's not actually true, because he could
inherit from his mother. So it's very funny why we say he's
like ליתא בירושה. leisa b'yerusha. He's like ליתא בירושה leisa b'yerusha through
patrilineal ירושה. yerusha. Right, right, I understand, I understand, but we know
that there is such a thing as inheriting from one's mother, okay?
But what we're saying is if somebody is, has no patrilineal, but
again, but you know it's still, so if somebody can't receive a
ירושה yerusha patrilineally, that's what we're saying, they can't be at the
recipient end of מתנת שכיב מרע. matnas shchiv meira. So a גר,
ger, either we're saying a גר ger can't gift a מתנת שכיב
מרע, matnas shchiv meira, or a גר ger can't can't receive a
מתנת שכיב מרע, matnas shchiv meira, okay? But that's an interesting exception
to the rule. The רשב"ם Rashbam reads it the second way, that
a גר ger can't receive a מתנת שכיב מרע matnas shchiv meira
because he's not in the position to inherit patrilineally. Okay, but so
that's a little bizarre because, you know, he is in some position
to inherit. But anyway, but again, you're seeing that even though the
language of מתנת שכיב מרע matnas shchiv meira is a language of
מתנה, matana,
at
least.
Yes so strictly רב מרי Rav Mari רב מרי Rav Mari is
a גר? ger? No רב מרי Rav Mari
is the child, I was making an analogy. He's the child who
does not have any father, but by analogy anybody who would be
a גר ger would also not be able to receive a מתנת
שכיב מרע matnat shechiv mera according to this.
Right right a גר ger right exactly.
Okay so okay so okay so he can't get a מתנה matana
so that's a nice new interesting הלכה halakha about מתנת שכיב מרע.
matnat shechiv mera. Okay so כל היכא דאמר kol heicha de'amar we
just did. אי במשיכה i bimeshicha alright let's let רב מרי Rav
Mari just come and do משיכה meshicha on the money. Okay רחוק
מגבי rachok migabei but he's off in ישיבה yeshiva learning, his father's
going to die any minute, he's not going to have time to
come here to my house to do a משיכה. meshicha. Okay אי
בחזקה i bechazaka of course you realize that what's going to happen
is is that if רב מרי Rav Mari has no way to
take possession of the money and איסור גיורא Issur Giyora dies, who's
going to get the money?
Whoever gets it.
רבא, Rava, who's in possession of it, because it would be a
גר שמת. ger shemet. So רבא Rava here is spelling out all
the reasons why רב מרי Rav Mari has no way of taking
possession of the money. Right? It becomes הפקר hefker and then since
it's in רבא's Rava possession he is the immediate one.
Can't he just give it to רב מרי? Rav Mari?
If he wanted to! Okay אי בחליפין i bechalipin he's trying to
he's trying to spell out why it is not possible for, okay,
אי בחליפין i bechalipin
ah let's just
get איסור גיורא Issur Giyora to do חליפין chalipin with the money
like to have his רב מרי Rav Mari give him a handkerchief
and then he'll take possession of the money. No אין מטבע נקנה
בחליפין. ein matbe'a nikna bechalipin. חליפין chalipin doesn't work on cash, on
coins, it only works on like קרקע ומטלטלין karka umitaltelin but not
on some... it doesn't work on cash. How about if he has
קרקע? karka? אי אגב קרקע i agav karka now how about let's
let איסור גיורא Issur Giyora give him a little piece of land,
a square inch of land, and with that square inch of land
we'll transfer the money because cash does get can you can take
possession of cash through taking possession of land. So לית ליה ארעא
leit lei ara he doesn't have any land. Of course now if
somebody was a friend of איסור גיורא Issur Giyora and knew about
this, he would give איסור גיורא Issur Giyora a square inch of
land and then איסור גיורא Issur Giyora could use it to transfer
his money to his son. Wait how איסור גיורא Issur Giyora can
give land and he can't give cash? Or why is it the
same set of cash? You could do it with חליפין chalipin just
transfer land with חליפין. chalipin. They don't have to be around. Somebody
else could take possession of the land for you, right? Anything else,
the חליפין chalipin is the one thing that you don't need you
know the object present and and you could always operate with a
third party doing it on behalf of someone. Okay
so but the other things like משיכה meshicha the money isn't present,
חליפין chalipin doesn't work for that, but let him do it with
קרקע karka and transfer קרקע karka to some third party on behalf
of רב מרי. Rav Mari. No לית ליה ארעא leit lei ara
he doesn't have. Of course there's a way to solve that but
okay. אי במעמד שלשתן i bama'amad shloshtan what if he asks me
to go there and me together with רב מרי Rav Mari to
go there and we'll all go there and then he'll transfer it
you know to רב מרי Rav Mari by מעמד שלשתן? ma'amad shloshtan?
I have to give him back the money and then he'll say
to me don't give me back the money, give it to רב
מרי. Rav Mari. So מעמד שלשתן ma'amad shloshtan works. אישלח לי לא
אזלינא. ishlach li lo azlina.
No! If he asks me to go I'm not going to show
up. I'm going to stay here which seems very clear that he's
doing this out of like self-interest, right? And I want to make
sure that he doesn't get that money to his biological son and
then I'll be able to take possession of it. Okay so
therefore there is no way he's going to do it and we're
going to have a lot of money coming into the ישיבה. yeshiva.
So מתקיף לה רב איקא בריה דרב אמי matkif lah Rav Ika
breih deRav Ami so רב איקא בריה דרב אמי Rav Ika breih
deRav Ami said אמאי amai what do you mean there's no way
he could do it? Here's a way he could do it. Okay
ואודי איסור דהני זוזי דרב מרי נינהו. ve'odei Issur dehanei zuzei deRav
Mari ninhu. Let him just admit in front of people and say
that money that רבא Rava has that he is holding on behalf
of me everybody should know that that money does not belong to
me actually last week I transferred it with a legitimate form of
קנין kinyan to
by giving קרקע karka to רב מרי. Rav Mari. Now it could
be that's completely not true, he didn't you know he didn't transfer
it to רב מרי, Rav Mari, but if he's admitting to that
in the presence of witnesses that'll be binding. Okay you got it?
So we knew that it's his money, he doesn't right now have
the forms of the קנינים kinyanim to do it, he doesn't have
קרקע, karka, he doesn't have this, he doesn't have that, but let
him just claim that a week ago, a year ago, whatever, he
transferred the money to רב מרי. Rav Mari. Okay and he makes
that claim in front of witnesses and now it's binding. Okay.
Isn't this very close to giving a gift? I mean the whole
concept here like you said that מתנת שכיב מרע matnat shechiv mera
isn't it very similar even though you just bought it?
Yes but it's doing it without the need of the קנין. kinyan.
It's doing it through a different method, through admitting. So it solves
the problem of those that messy need for doing the קנין kinyan
in the right way.
Exactly, and רבא Rava basically you're saying lying under oath solves the
problem?
Yeah you don't have to be under oath. It's in front of
witnesses, I mean it's not oath, it's understood, it's also like a
little bit of a fiction. Like it's understood that if you're making
a
Well yes because you're right now even though the guy's about to
die right now it's his property. So it's right now we assess
right now you're taking a claim about your own property. הודאת בעל
דין כמאה עדים דמי hoda'at ba'al din k'me'ah edim dami to go
to his son. But it doesn't matter if against this person right
doesn't matter long term it's going to be hurting Rava and helping
his biological son. Right now he's saying money that everybody thinks is
mine is not mine belongs to somebody else. Okay so מתקיף matkif
so לא ולודי la v'lodi וקנינו באודיתא v'kaninu b'udita now again the
very fact that this is a fiction you see by these words
let him קונה koneh it through the admission okay הודאה hoda'ah אודיתא
udita so it's all of like it becomes an act of a
קנין. kinyan. It's not really an act of קנין kinyan but we
all know that it's not true but by saying it and admitting
to it in front of witnesses it effectively makes it true it
creates it's it becomes like a קנין. kinyan. So let him קונה
koneh it through the admission. So אדהכי נפק אודיתא מבי איסר ad-hachi
nafak udita mi-bei issur so as so then so then what happened
was that they were talking about it and word got back to
Issur Giyora and lo and behold Issur Giyora made this admission and
he accomplished what he was trying to accomplish give the money to
his biological son. He heard about this that there was this way
to do it. איקפד רבא ikpad rava Rava was upset. אמר קא
מגמרי טענתא לאינשי ומפסדי לי amar ka magmrei ta'anta l'inshei umasdei li
you're giving advice to other people and you're hurting my own interests.
Now this is a very disturbing story. Why is it a disturbing
story? First of all the language you're teaching other people a טענה.
ta'ana. טענה ta'ana is sort of like if we're in court and
litigating and somebody is whispering in your ear a way to say
something okay that's like a טענה ta'ana that's a claim and that
you could say is maybe I mean this is why the Gemara
didn't always like didn't really like lawyers is because you know you
could have a claim that wins in court that's actually like false
right so people are maybe teaching you how to lie and how
to win in court even though it's not the truth. That's the
normal use of the word טענה. ta'ana. You know so somebody told
my litigant something and gave him advice to in court to win
and it's hurting my own interest and this is my and I
deserve the money. That's completely not what's going on here right what's
going on here is that the person who owned the money wanted
to give the money to his biological son and is trying to
do what he should be able to do with his own money
and נעבעך nebech Rava is losing out from the ability to seize
that property for himself which is not the will of the person
who right now owns it. So the claim teaching somebody else a
טענה ta'ana that they can hurt my own interest seems very non
accurate self-interested way of describing the reality and the whole thing is
deeply disturbing right that Rava is trying to subvert what seems to
be the interests of the owner of the property particularly property that
he has been given for safe keeping. So it
was very interesting I
looked
this up in the Soncino and I started reading a footnote
in the Soncino which to me was so apologetic it sounded like
the ArtScroll okay I could not believe that I was reading this
in the Soncino and I want to read you this footnote in
the Soncino listen to this it says
it is possible that Rava had no intention whatsoever to appropriate Issur's
money and the whole discussion of the possible legal means whereby Rav
Mari could acquire possession of his father's money was only a master's
method of impressing the subtle laws upon his students' minds none of
his academy suspected for one moment that the master would in all
earnestness desire to retain the money he held as a deposit from
one who obviously confided in him had Rava been in earnest he
would not have spoken publicly about such a matter when he knew
well that Issur was still alive and could find legal means to
transfer for a son if not to reclaim the deposit himself Rava's
pretended annoyance and an ironic exclamation that these people to say what
to say and cause me a loss must have been just a
mild chiding to the students or their friends who deprived him of
the satisfaction of passing on the money to Rav Mari as a
generous gift rather than legally due to him anyway the fact that
mention that Rav Mari was at a master's house a school which
has no point receives no significance it was discussed by Rava publicly
despite the fact that Rav Mari himself was at school perhaps Rava's
own school and would well be aware of the discussion and could
report it to his father the mention of Rav Mari's presence was
probably the key indication of Rava's integrity and honor. So that was
a pretty long footnote
of apologetics my guess has something to do with the fact that
the
Soncino was whatever it's probably they were very concerned about the often
the ArtScroll's apologetics are very
similar yeah often say he really wanted to give I know often
look maybe it's true but nevertheless often the
ArtScroll I think
the apologetics are directed though at different audiences. Whereas I think the
Soncino's apologetics are directed at the non-Jews that might be reading. If
you think about when and the context in which the Soncino was
written, you know, in England and so on, whatever, I don't think,
I think that there, probably the Soncino was not as popular of
a work and was a way in which non-Jews got access to
the תלמוד *Talmud*, right? So you know, so I think that that
was an apologetic directed more to non-Jews. Yes.
And today the Soncino translation is online for free to anybody.
There you go.
Steinsaltz actually quotes the idea that רבא *Rava* didn't want to keep
it in the name of רבינו יונתן *Rabbenu Yonatan* of Lunel.
Oh yeah? That's interesting. That's a ראשון *Rishon*, that's an early ראשון
*Rishon*. He's the same generation as the רמבם
*Rambam*.
Very early, yeah.
Right. Okay. Okay. So it is interesting that רבא *Rava's* sort of
like discussing the matter, oh he can't do this, he can't do
that, he can't do this. I think it is definitely a possible
read, okay? But it's still interesting, you know, like said he was
using it as a way of like discussing the issue. But anyway,
what we find from it is that a שכיב מרע shekhiv mera,
*shachiv meyra* if he does do a הודאה *hoda'ah*, it is effective,
and we don't say he's just doing it so his kids look
rich. So the רשבם *Rashbam* says so how does this work
with
the other סוגיא *sugya* that if a שכיב מרע *shachiv meyra* says,
"Oh, I owe a million dollars to so-and-so," that we don't believe
him and that we say that he's just doing it so that
his sons don't look wealthy and people don't take advantage of them?
So the רשבם *Rashbam* says it's different whether you're claiming a debt
or whether you're claiming that a specific piece of property belongs to
somebody else. To claim a debt, when people hear, "Oh my gosh,
the whole estate has all of this- is saddled with all of
this debt," right? So that changes people's perception of the estate. It's
also to be in debt
is not a status that people want. You don't want to be
seen as being in debt to other people. So in that type
of a case we say he's doing it just to make his
kids look bad, you know, bad for a good, whatever, so people
don't take advantage of them. Whereas when you say a specific piece
of property belongs to somebody else, okay, then that's much more specific
and concrete and so on and therefore we're actually going to have
that take the normal effect of an admission and say that therefore
now we will give that piece of property to the other person
without a קנין *kinyan*, but because you admitted it and that admission
is binding. Okay, so that's a very interesting new idea here about
what's called almost a קנין אודיתא *Kinyan Odita* sometimes how it gets
reframed because you can let him- you can let him קונה *kone*
it through an אודיתא *odita*, through a הודאה *hoda'ah*. It says it
almost like replaces the need for a קנין *kinyan* and sometimes even
gets called as a type of a קנין *kinyan*, but it works
through testifying against yourself. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*... yes...
is there any parallel between this story and the אונקלוס *Onkelos* story?
Not in terms of the הלכות halachot *halachos* but in terms of
like, you know, this...
Oh, you mean a non-Jew and then he wanted to marry... right,
interesting... yeah, that's interesting...
if I understand תוספות *Tosafot* correctly, if they actually raise a קשיא
*kashya* against רבא *Rava*, למה לא מצוה לקיים דברי המת *lama lo
mitzvah lekayem divrei hameit*? Right.
So we- so what- yes, so what we haven't seen yet, which
I was sort of holding off on, but it's okay, is that
in addition- I think I mentioned it- I did mention it earlier.
In addition to מתנת שכיב מרע matnas shechiv mera *matnat shachiv meyra*,
which is automatically binding and the money transfers, and then there's- there's
this other category which is basically like, you know- I said like
there's an ethical will, I'm just leaving my wisdom to my children,
but then there's a category between the two which is, I am-
what's sort of the פשט *pshat* of the פסוקים *psukim* that he's
מצוה על ביתו *metzaveh al beito*, where he leaves instructions with what
he wants to be done with his property, but it's not an
actual transfer of the property, right? I want to make sure that
you always, you know- right, you always, you know- you always, you
know- you use money from our account to bring over your cousins
every חנוכה *Hanukkah*, you know, wherever they happen to be, you know,
you pay for their whatever. Okay, he didn't transfer any money, but
it's his wishes, right? So that's מצוה לקיים דברי המת *mitzvah lekayem
divrei hameit*. Sort of the wishes that are expressed, you know, that-
that's not legally binding and it doesn't cause a legal transfer of
property, but the heirs- there's a מצוה *mitzvah*, which doesn't mean it's
legally binding, but if they're doing the right thing, they're supposed to
go ahead and do the wishes of the person who died. Okay,
and so that's a separate question. So that was what תוספות *Tosafot*
was asking, that wouldn't רבא *Rava* be obligated to give the money
to מרי בר רחל *Mari bar Rachel* if that's what איסור גיורא
*Issur Giyora* had said to him and wanted, even if- even if
he couldn't legally transfer it to מרי בר רחל *Mari bar Rachel*,
wouldn't at least רבא *Rava* be obligated to do it because of
מצוה לקיים דברי המת *mitzvah lekayem divrei hameit*? Okay, so that's what
תוספות *Tosafot* is asking. So that's this new concept, okay? And then
we- we won't go into exactly whatever, but that doesn't apply in
all cases. Okay, so we'll see more that later. Let's turn- let's
try to finish the דף *daf*.
And now we finally get- so there should have been two dots,
it's a little confusing because we're on a new topic. Right now,
now we're going to get on this definition of what is it
when, what is the case of מקצת? mikzas. What is the case
when it doesn't work within the מתנת שכיב מרע matnas shechiv mera.
context? So the משנה mishnah said you left over a little bit
of land. Does it have to be land? So let's take a
look what the גמרא Gemara. says. שייר קרקע כל שהוא מתנתו קיימת.
shayar karka kol shehu matnaso kayames.
If you left over a little bit of land, then even if
the guy gets better, it's still binding. It's not מתנת שכיב מרע.
וכמה כל
שהוא? vekama kol shehu? You gotta love the גמרא. Gemara How much
is even the tiniest amount? Okay? So אמר רב יהודה אמר רב,
amar Rav Yehuda amar Rav, קרקע כדי פרנסתו. karka kidei parnasaso. It
doesn't literally mean the tiniest amount. It means enough that you could
support the guy, okay? Because the whole point is, the fact that
he's leaving over property shows that he really that he wants to
make sure that even if he gets better, he won't be left
penniless and he'll still be able to pray for his, you know,
for his basic necessities. So that's what how you define it. You
determine what is this guy's basic necessities? And if he's leaving over
enough to support his basic, like cost of living, you know, then
that means that he wants it to be binding even if he
gets better. And that's מקצת. Now that's not a tiny amount, right?
'Cause he could live for another ten years, right? So כדי פרנסתו
kidei parnasaso could be, you know, you know, you need a lot
of money in the bank to make sure, you know, to live
off of.
So this כל שהוא kol shehu is a different כל שהוא.
kol shehu. Well, that's what the גמרא Gemara is going to discuss.
Okay. רב ירמיא בר אבא, Rav Yirmiya bar Abba, אמר, amar, once
we're saying that it's not that that's true, מטלטלין כדי פרנסתו, metaltelin
kidei parnasaso, even if it's not קרקע. karka. Even if he left
over, I don't know, if he had a million dollars in the
bank, okay, and he could live off of the interest of that
to pay for his, you know, for his living expenses, that would
be enough. Okay, but it has to be enough to pay for
his living expenses. So אמר רבי זירא, amar Rabbi Zeira, כמה מכוונין
שמעתתא דסבי. kama mechavnin shemaata desavei. So how how like, you know,
in line or like, you know, how like,
what's a good word?
Like, I don't know, precise.
Yeah, but it's not exactly precise. But maybe precise. But it's more
like, you know, how like perfectly attuned, you know, is the teachings
of of these elders. Because that they say that we don't they,
you know, that they're they're very smart to get to the deeper
meaning and not to be overly literal is what he's saying. מאי
טעמא, mai taama, why do we say it's supposed to be land?
דאי קאי, de'i kai, because if he gets better, סמיך עליה. samich
alei. Land classically is something you can plant and harvest and it
could provide an ongoing support. So once it's about providing ongoing support,
why not just translate that into the equivalent if it's cash? You
know, for chattel, מטלטלין נמי קאי סמיך עליה. metaltelin nami kai samich
alei. So as long as you have enough, you know, מטלטלין, metaltelin,
enough chattel that will effectively do the same, קרקע karka should not
be overly literally read overly literally. Okay, the importance of קרקע karka
is that it's, you know, if you have a certain size of
land, then you can at least provide for your own personal needs,
you know, on an ongoing basis. So if you have that equivalency
in cash or in, you know, chattel, then that should be the
same. Okay, so he says this is very smart because you're getting
to what the real reason is about. So מתקיף לה רב יוסף,
maskif lah Rav Yosef, רב יוסף Rav Yosef said, ומאי כוונתו? umai
kavanaso? What's so sort of in tune about that meeting?
מן דאמר מטלטלין, man de'amar metaltelin, because, you know, it's all very
nice you think that it's getting to the deeper reading, but it's
completely violating what what actually was said. Okay. So if the one
is saying מטלטלין, metaltelin, קרקע תנן! karka tenan! It says land! Land
we taught! מן דאמר כדי פרנסתו, man de'amar kidei parnasaso, and the
one that says, "Oh but we just it means it's enough to
support you," כל שהוא תנן! kol shehu tenan! But it says even
the smallest amount! So that's very interesting, right? How much are you
sort of going by the literal meaning of the text, or you're
saying, "Let's get to what it's really all about?" So אמר ליה
אביי, amar lei Abaye, so now אביי's Abaye going to push back.
Maybe we don't have to be so so overly literal.
וכל היכא דתני קרקע קרקע דוקא? vechol heicha detani karka karka davka?
Do you think every time a something says land, it means land
only and not מטלטלין? metaltelin? I mean normally we should, but he
says there are exceptions. והתנן, vehasnan, we taught in the משנה, mishnah,
הכותב נכסיו וכל נכסיו לעבדו
יצא בן חורין. hakosev nechasav vechol nechasav le'avdo yatza ben chorin. Somebody
writes over to his slave
all of my property is given to you for a gift, and
gives that charge to his slave, his slave goes free and gets
all the property. You know why the slave goes free?
Why do you think the slave goes free?
He didn't free the slave, he just said I'm giving you all
my property.
The slave was was part of the property, the slave
is part of the property, so he's giving the slave to himself.
So the slave goes free. שייר קרקע כל שהוא, shayar karka kol
shehu, let's say however he says to the slave, "I'm giving you
all my property except for a little bit of land." And he
doesn't say what land. He doesn't say this field. He says a
little bit of land. לא יצא בן חורין, lo yatza ben chorin,
he doesn't go free. You know why? 'Cause a slave is considered
קרקע. karka. So we assume that the קרקע כל שהוא karka kol
shehu means except for you, okay? And therefore the slave doesn't go
free and the slave also didn't take possession of the property, so
the whole thing becomes void. רבי שמעון אומר לעולם הוא בן חורין
עד שיאמר כל נכסי נתונים לפלוני עבדי חוץ מאחד מריבוא שבהן. Rabbi
Shimon omer le'olam hu ben chorin ad sheyomar kol nechasai nesunin leploni
avdi chutz me'echad meribbo shebahen. No, he says... If you use the
language קרקע, karqa, you are not referring to the slave. So if
you say you get it all except for a little bit of
land, the slave does go free. You know the one case the
slave does not go free? If you say I'm giving you all
of my property except for one ten thousandth, one one hundredth of
a percent. Since you're not specifically identifying, even if you're saying a
tiny amount, that might mean except for you yourself. Okay? But if
you say except for land, even if slave halachically is in the
category of קרקע, karqa, it would not be what you would mean
when you would say except for land would not mean except for
you. But except for a tenth of a percent, maybe you're the
person who's in the tenth of the percent category. Okay fine, that's
that debate, but that's not interesting to us. What's interesting to us
is חוץ מקרקע, chutz me-karqa, the slave doesn't go free according to
the תנא קמא. Tanna Kamma. Now, we're going to say קרקע karqa
doesn't mean קרקע. karqa. ואמר Ve-amar top of קנ עמוד א, Kuf
Nun Amud Aleph, look at this, we got ahead. ואמר רב דימי
בר יוסף אמר רבי אלעזר עשו מטלטלין שיור אצל עבד. Ve-amar Rav
Dimi bar Yosef amar Rabbi Elazar asu metalletalin shiyur etzel eved. If
you say except for a little מטלטלין, metalletalin, again you don't say
which מטלטלין, metalletalin, you're just generic. Except for a little מטלטלין, metalletalin,
also the slave doesn't go free, because when people say the word
מטלטלין, metalletalin, they mean, when they say the word קרקע karqa they
could refer to a slave because halachically he's treated like קרקע, karqa,
but מטלטלין metalletalin they could also refer to him because he moves
around, he is like chattel, he's not stable like קרקע. karqa. So
that also would be say the slave does not go free. Okay,
ולא עשו מטלטלין שיור אצל כתובה. ve-lo asu metalletalin shiyur etzel ketubbah.
However, if you remember back we had a case that if a
man is distributing all of his property
to
his kids and gives his wife a piece of קרקע, karqa, then
that piece of קרקע karqa under certain circumstances is in substitute of
her כתובה. ketubbah. Right, do you remember that? And it's like she's
being מוחל mochel on the rest of her כתובה. ketubbah. So but
if he gave her some מטלטלין, metalletalin, it would not be a
מוחל mochel on the כתובה, ketubbah, it would not be considered a
payment of the כתובה. ketubbah. Fine, that's not so relevant for us.
What's relevant for us is it says קרקע karqa in the משנה
Mishnah that if you say except for קרקע karqa the slave doesn't
go free, and להלכה le-halacha we say it's not limited to קרקע.
karqa. Even if you say except for מטלטלין, metalletalin, the slave does
not go free. So you see that קרקע karqa doesn't always have
to mean literally קרקע. karqa. So the גמרא Gemara says like this:
No, it's not a good proof. The גמרא says like this: התם
משום דלא פשני קרקע. Hatam mishum de-lo pashni karqa.
You're right, it should have said חוץ מקרקע, chutz me-karqa, it should
have said חוץ מקרקע או מטלטלין chutz me-karqa o metalletalin or whatever
it should have said. ואיידי דתנא רישא, Ve-aydi de-tana resha,
but since the beginning of the משנה Mishnah was very specific about
קרקע. karqa. How is the beginning of the משנה Mishnah very specific
about קרקע? karqa? Because here's what it said: רבי עקיבא אומר, Rabbi
Akiva Omer, this might you might be familiar with this, we've quoted
it before, קרקע כל שהוא karqa kol shehu even a smallest piece
of land חייבת בפאה, chayyavet be-pe'ah, you would have to leave over
a corner, even if it was a tiny patch of land, ובביכורים
u-vi-bikkurim you'd have to bring ביכורים bikkurim from it, ולכתוב עליהם פרוזבול,
ve-likhtov aleihem prosbul, it's big enough to use a פרוזבול, prosbul, the
פרוזבול prosbul that prevents the debts getting annulled requires that there be
a little bit of land that the is owned by the by
the debtor because then it's like the creditor has the property there
to seize from and and like it's like it's already to some
degree under the control of the creditor, so that's allows the פרוזבול
prosbul to work, ולקנות עמהם נכסים שאינם אחריות בכסף ובשטר ובחזקה. ve-liknot
immahem nechasim she-einam achrayut be-khesef u-vishtar u-ve-chazaqah.
And if you transfer a little bit of land to somebody, then
with that you can transfer chattel. Okay? So by taking possession of
the land you take possession of the chattel. So there we were
teaching about all of these הלכות halachot are הלכות that require קרקע.
karqa. So since the beginning of the משנה Mishnah mentioned קרקע, karqa,
when we got to this idea we said חוץ מקרקע. chutz me-karqa.
But it really wasn't limited to קרקע. karqa. Okay, so because of
that משום הכי תנא קרקע. mishum hachi tana karqa. Okay, but there
there's a reason it says קרקע karqa even though it's לאו דוקא.
lav davqa. You're right. חוץ מקרקע, chutz me-karqa, חוץ ממטלטלין chutz mi-metalletalin
would exclude the עבד. eved. But we said קרקע karqa because we
had been talking about קרקע. karqa. So there was a reason. So
can a word sometimes be לאו דוקא? lav davqa? Yes, but you
have to explain why we used it if it wasn't meant literally.
And there there's an explanation why we use it if it wasn't
meant literally. Here when you're talking about a שכיב מרע, why would
you say שיור קרקע כל שהוא shiyur karqa kol shehu if you
didn't literally mean קרקע? karqa? Okay? So this is the pushback. I
don't like the idea that you're saying Oh, we know what it
means and it doesn't have to be about קרקע, karqa, we know
what it's about. The משנה Mishnah says קרקע. karqa. And don't tell
me קרקע karqa is לאו דוקא, lav davqa, sometimes something is not
literal but that's when there's a reason why that word was used,
why there's some why would we have said it if it wasn't
literal? Well because we were talking about קרקע. karqa. But here there's
no good reason unless we mean it literally. Okay? And now we're
going to continue tomorrow to discuss whether כל שהוא kol shehu always
means כל שהוא kol shehu or whether כל שהוא kol shehu sometimes
can mean a certain מין. min.